Guide to the Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes Papers, 1811-1990s and undated (bulk 1905-1981)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes papers 1811-1990s and undated, bulk 1905-1981
Gohdes, Clarence, 1901
6.2 linear feet Extent: 4650 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00458
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes in 1983, with additional materials received through 2000.
Biographical Note
1901, July 2 Born, San Antonio, Tex.
1921 A.B., Capital University, Columbus, Ohio
1922 A.M., Ohio State University
1926-1927 Assistant Professor of English, Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Tex.
1928 M.A., Harvard University
1929-1930 Instructor in English, New York University
1930-1938 Assistant and Associate Professor of English, Duke University
1931 Ph.D., Columbia University Published The Periodicals of American Transcendentalism
1932-1954 Managing Editor, American Literature (journal)
1932 Published Uncollected Lectures of Ralph Waldo Emerson: Reports on American Life and Natural Religion (editor) Visiting lecturer, Columbia University
1938 Married Celestine Marie Beamer
1938-1961 Professor of English, Duke University
1944 Published American Literature in Nineteenth-Century England
1949 Published Faint Clews and Indirections: Manuscripts of Walt Whitman and His Family (co-editor)
1951 Published Literature of the American People (contributor)
1954-1969 Editor-in-chief, American Literature (journal)
1955 Published America's Literature (co-editor)
1959 Published Bibliographical Guide to the Study of the Literature of the U.S.A. Served as Chairman, Modern Language Association, American Literature Group
1961-1971 James B. Duke Professor of American Literature, Duke University
1962 Guggenheim Fellow
1967 Published Essays on American Literature in Honor of Jay B. Hubbell (editor) Published Hunting in the Old South (editor) Published Literature and Theater of the States and Regions of the U.S.A.: A Historical Bibliography
1971 Retired from Duke University
1982 Published Scuppernong, North Carolina's Grape and Its Wines
1988 Published Pioneers in English at Trinity and Duke
1997 Died, Durham, N.C.
Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes began his post-undergraduate studies at Harvard, where he turned his attention from Latin to American literature under the tutelage of Bliss Perry, J. L. Lowes, G. L. Kittredge, and Kenneth B. Murdock. At Columbia, Gohdes wrote his dissertation under Ralph L. Rusk.
Gohdes earned his scholarly reputation through his work in American literature. He published two texts, one on Ralph Waldo Emerson and the other on Walt Whitman, that contributed to American literary scholarship through his original research and archival work. Gohdes also influenced the formation of American literary studies through his long-standing position as Managing Editor (under Jay B. Hubbell, founding editor) and then Editor-in-Chief of American Literature, the discipline's foundational academic journal. Similarly, Gohdes's A Bibliographical Guide to the Study of the Literature of the U.S.A., which went through five editions, played a key role in documenting and making accessible American literary criticism. Gohdes's career achievements attest to his role in extending the work of scholars of American literature.
Collection Overview
The Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes Papers date from 1811 to the 1990s, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1905 to 1981. The collection consists of research materials, correspondence, writings, clippings and other printed materials, and a few photographs, mainly from the latter half of Gohdes's career. The earliest date (1811) refers to reproductions of original materials used in his research. Correspondence with other American Literature teachers and authors, combined with other materials relating to Gohdes's institutional and organizational affiliations, in particular with Duke University, the Modern Language Association (MLA), and American Literature, comprise the most substantive aspects of this collection. They provide insight into the bureaucratic and institutional exigencies of American literary scholarship in the mid-twentieth century. Major authors and scholars of the time wrote to Gohdes, and include Alexander Blackburn, Oscar Cargill, Lewis Chase, Robert Elias, Norman Foerster, Arthur Rubin, Arthur Quinn, and Upton Sinclair. Original manuscripts by Gohdes, inscribed reprints of writings by his colleagues, and materials relating to many major British and American literary figures, make up the rest of the collection. There is substantial material on Edgar Allen Poe. The collection also includes papers documenting his research and writing for his last book project, a cultural and horticultural history of the scuppernong grape entitled Scuppernong, North Carolina's Grape and Its Wines. The Gohdes Papers are divided into seven series: Biographical Data, Correspondence, Author Files, Subject Files, Writings and Speeches, Scuppernong, and Clippings.
The Biographical Data Series briefly sketches the major events of Gohdes's life. It consists of only a few items, including a one-page sketch by Gohdes of his career's highlights, and photocopies of Gohdes's obituaries. Further biographical information, especially pertaining to Gohdes's academic life, can be culled from materials in the Correspondence Series.
The Correspondence Series contains letters exchanged with university administrators, publishers, colleagues, librarians, and literary figures. The series is divided into four subseries, American Literature, Lewis Chase, Duke University, and General. The bulk of the correspondence concerns professional and academic affairs, such as appointments, editorships, research and reviews, and publishing. Included are exchanges between Gohdes and Duke University administrators about English Department and American Literature affairs, as well as between Gohdes and contemporary literary critics about the study of American literature. There are also several documents that illuminate Gohdes's political affiliations and social concerns.
Materials on approximately fifty authors, largely major British and American writers, are in the Author Files Series and were originally gathered by Gohdes and his colleague, Lewis Chase. The folders contain a variety of information on the represented authors, in an equally varied mix of formats: clippings, notes, lectures, student papers, photographs, and reproductions or photocopies of original writing.
Included in the Subject Files Series are materials relating to several projects and interests which engaged Gohdes during his career. These include: bibliographies, poetry, travel narratives and the American West, and the United Nations' Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO)/American Literature Section's Best American Books List. The bibliographies collected in this series reflect Gohdes's interest in this genre, as he participated in and edited many such projects throughout his career.
The Writings and Speeches Series contains manuscript and printed materials in two subseries: Writings by Gohdes and Writings by Others. The Writings by Gohdes Subseries includes manuscripts of short stories, poetry, and academic essays, as well as notes and notecards. The manuscripts also contain folders pertaining to unfinished projects and writings. The Writings by Gohdes Subseries also contains several folders of printed materials, consisting of reprints and reproductions of as well as advertising and promotional materials for Gohdes's published writings. This subseries consists almost entirely of reprints that are inscribed to Gohdes by the authors.
Materials relating to the writing and research of Gohdes's last published book, Scuppernong, North Carolina's Grape and Its Wines, are in the Scuppernong Series. Three subseries make up this series: Correspondence, Research and Notes, and Publication Materials. Correspondence plus photocopied articles and essays about the grape and agricultural production form the bulk of the series. Also included are Gohdes's many notes and notecards, as well as reviews and materials relating to the book's publication.
The Clippings Series contains the few clippings that are not housed in the Author Files Series. These clippings mostly consist of articles relating to literary figures.
Related collections in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library include the records of American Literature and the Modern Language Association's American Literature Section, as well as the papers of many of Gohdes's colleagues, such as Jay B. Hubbell and Arlin Turner.
Processing Note:
Roman numerals have been appended to certain folders, such as the Contemporary Poetry Selections, to indicate when Gohdes's original folders had the same title for distinct groups of materials, and to maintain such original distinctions.
Subject Headings
Gohdes, Clarence Louis Frank, 1901-; Blackburn, Alexander; Cargill, Oscar, 1898-; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849; Elias, Robert H.; Foerster, Norman, 1887-; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Rubin, Arthur; Quinn, Arthur Hobson, 1875-1960; Chase, Lewis Nathaniel, 1873-1937; Duke University. Dept. of English -- Faculty; Modern Language Association. American Literature Section; American literature -- Study and teaching; American Literature (Durham, N.C.); American literature -- History and criticism; College teachers -- Correspondence; Black-and-white photographs; Muscadine grape -- North Carolina; Viticulture -- North Carolina; Wine and wine making -- North Carolina
Contents of Collection
- Biographical Data Series, after 1959 and 1997
  Contains a brief document resembling a curriculum vita, and clippings of obituaries. Further details of Gohdes's career can be found in the Correspondence and Writings and Speeches series. In particular, the American Literature and Duke University correspondence files provide information about Gohdes's professional life.
  - Biographical Sketch, after 1959 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 1997 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1926-1989 and undated, bulk 1928-1967 (Box 1)
  Chiefly concerns professional and academic interests. The series is divided into four sections: American Literature, Lewis Chase, Duke University, and General.
  The American Literature correspondence mainly addresses administrative issues and editorial appointments. In particular, the letters represent discussions among Gohdes, Duke administrators, the American Literature editorial board, and representatives of the American Literature Section (ALS) of the Modern Language Association over a 1966-1968 reworking of the contractual agreement between Duke and the ALS.
  The Lewis Chase correspondence contains letters exchanged between him and libraries and colleagues. All letters concern Chase's research on Edgar Allen Poe.
  Duke University Correspondence contains letters about Gohdes's discussions with the University and its English department over hiring, tenure, and his professorship. Included is a series of letters between Arlin Turner, Gohdes, and the administration that concerns a disagreement over the editorship of American Literature. The group also contains one letter from Lyne S. Few, son of William Preston Few, that recounts his memories of Duke faculty and his father's role at Duke. It was written in response to reading Gohdes's booklet, Pioneers in English at Trinity and Duke.
  The General Correspondence includes letters from colleagues and peers, contemporary authors, and publishers and librarians. The main topics of discussion are professional, such as job appointments and recommendations, research and reviews, and publishing. The files include letters exchanged with some of the major scholars and authors of the day: Alexander Blackburn, Walter Blair, Van Wyck Brooks, Oscar Cargill, Robert Elias, Norman Foerster, Ima Honaker Herron, James Meriwether, Perry Miller, William Mulder, Arthur Quinn, Louis Rubin, Arthur M. Schlesinger (single item), Upton Sinclair, Henry Nash Smith, Robert Spiller, George R. Stewart, and George F. Whicher. Substantial correspondence exists between Gohdes and Thomas O. Mabbott, Henry A. Pochmann, and James Woodress. Other items of interest include a letter from Martha Baird (Mrs. Eli Siegel) to Gohdes which includes a copy of a letter from William Carlos Williams, letters exchanged with Clayton L. Eichelberger concerning the establishment of American Literary Realism (journal), and invitations to Richard Nixon's 1971 and Ronald Reagan's 1985 inaugurations. Gohdes saved several form letters from major intellectual and political leaders: Albert Einstein; Archibald MacLeish; Richard M. Nixon; Pearl S. Buck; Jacques Cousteau; and Nancy Reagan (letter contains autograph). Arranged chronologically by date within each section.
  - American Literature, 1928-1968, bulk 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Chase, Lewis, 1931-1938 and undated (Box 1)
  - Duke University, 1938-1989 (Box 1)
  - General, 1926-1985 and undated, bulk 1964-1967, (7 folders) (Box 1)
- Author Files Series, 1899-1964 and undated (Box 1)
  Consists of clippings, student papers, and notes. Some author files contain only printed materials or other non-original materials. Some, however, contain original notes, lectures, or early twentieth-century student papers. Lectures, usually by Lewis Chase, provide insight into turn-of-the-century literary perspectives on major authors from Poe to Shakespeare. The student papers suggest the scope and range of literary training and pedagogy at this moment in history.
  This series contains a large amount of material belonging to Dr. Lewis Chase (1873-1937). It seems that many unattributed items and folders came from Chase, including all student papers. The files which contain material compiled or created by Gohdes include those on Anderson, Dickinson, Dreiser, Eliot, Emerson, Faulkner, Fitzgerald, Frost, Garland, Holmes, Howells, James, Lanier, Longfellow, O'Neill, Ransom, Twain, and Updike. In particular, the Emerson "Notes" and Longfellow folders include substantial original materials by Gohdes. The rest of the folders seem to be heavily weighted to Chase materials, with only some of Gohdes's resources added. Most of the British authors are from Chase, whereas Gohdes is responsible for the American author materials.
  Several of the author files contain photocopies of selections or excerpts from the author's writing, for example, most of the Twain and all of the Sidgwick folders. "Mark Twain's Funniest" folders seem to have been one of Gohdes's projects.
  Within each folder, arranged alphabetically by author, items are arranged chronologically. Author names have been standardized on folder titles.
  - Anderson, Maxwell (Box 2)
    - Press release, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Dickinson, Emily (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1945-1946 and undated (Box 2)
  - Drinkwater, John (Box 2)
    - Mary Stuart Clipping, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Dreiser, Theodore (Box 2)
    - Press release, circa 1944 (Box 2)
  - Eliot, T.S. (Box 2)
    - Phonograph recording of Eliot reading selections of his poems, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (Box 2)
    - Clippings and printed materials, 1903-1941 and undated (Box 2)
    - Notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Faulkner, William (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1950-1956 and undated (Box 2)
    - Notes and lectures, 1958 and undated (Box 2)
  - Fitzgerald, F. Scott (Box 2)
    - Clipping, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Frost, Robert (Box 2)
    - Printed materials, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Garland, Hamlin (Box 2)
    - Thesis abstract, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Holmes, Oliver W. (Box 2)
    - Engraving, undated (Box 2)
  - Howells, William Dean (Box 2)
    - Criticism: printed materials, 1944-1958 (Box 2)
  - James, Henry (Box 2)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Lanier, Sidney (Box 2)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Research and essays, 1931-1942 and undated (Box 2)
  - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth (Box 2)
    - Longfellow in England [Notes], undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Notes and clippings, 1963 and undated (Box 2)
  - O'Neill, Eugene (Box 2)
    - Clippings and criticism, 1946-1960 and undated (Box 2)
  - Poe, Edgar (Box 2)
    - Poeiana, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Reviews and criticism (Box 2)
      - Baxter, W. E., "Stoke Newington and English Literature," 1914 (Box 2)
      - Chase, Lewis, "Poe's 'Ulalume': Two Interpretations," undated (Box 2)
      - Cox, Fay, " Graham's Magazine and Edgar Allen Poe," 1930 (Box 2)
      - Dowler, C. X., "Notes on Parodies of Poe's The Raven," undated (Box 2)
      - Krutch, Joseph Wood, 1926-1932 and undated (Box 2)
      - Mabbott, T. O., 1926 (Box 2)
      - Waldron, M. P., "The Boyhood of Edgar Allen Poe," undated (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
      - Borough of Stoke Newington Public Library Annual Report, 1913-1914 (Box 2)
      - Clarence Bringham and Lewis Chase correspondence, 1932-1934 and undated (Box 2)
      - Clippings, 1915-1943 (Box 2)
      - Memorabilia, undated (Box 2)
      - Poe, 1941 clippings, 1941-1943 (Box 2)
      - Poe shrine, 1921-1934 (Box 2)
      - Poe Society, 1929-1935 (Box 2)
      - Poe's wife, clippings, 1928 and undated (Box 3)
      - "The Raven" clippings, 1924-1931 (Box 3)
  - Ransom, John Crowe (Box 3)
    - Notes and text, undated (Box 3)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington (Box 3)
    - Criticism: printed materials, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Scott, Sir Walter (Box 3)
    - Chase, Lewis on "The Battle of Flodder," 1925 (Box 3)
    - Lectures on "Fortunes of Nigle," undated (Box 3)
    - Notes, undated (Box 3)
    - "Scott as a Poet," undated (Box 3)
    - Student papers, 1908 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Shadwell, Thomas (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1906-1937 (Box 3)
  - Settle, Elkanah (Box 3)
    - Lewis Chase's notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Shakespeare, William (Box 3)
    - Sonnets (Box 3)
      - Clippings, 1904-1905 (Box 3)
      - General, 1935 and undated (Box 3)
      - Student papers, undated (Box 3)
    - Plays (Box 3)
      - As You Like It - Lewis Chase's notes, 1903 and undated (Box 3)
      - Hamlet - Notes and clippings, 1937-1940 and undated (Box 3)
      - King John - Notes, undated (Box 3)
      - Macbeth - Notes, undated (Box 3)
      - Othello, Lewis Chase's notes, undated (Box 3)
      - The Tempest, Chase's notes, undated (Box 3)
      - Twelfth Night, Chase's notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Research and Information, 1903-1941 and undated (Box 3)
      - Acting of Shakespeare, 1911 and undated (Box 3)
      - Criticism: printed materials, 1916-1935 and undated (Box 3)
      - Clippings, 1911-1941 and undated (Box 3)
      - Folger Library, 1931-1936 and undated (Box 3)
      - General, undated (Box 3)
      - History of Shakespeare criticism - notes, undated (Box 3)
      - Lectures, 1903 Dec. (Box 3)
      - Shakespeare Association, 1927 (Box 3)
      - Shakespeare in France, 1909 (Box 3)
      - Shakespearean Myth, 1912 (Box 4)
      - Stratford: photographs of players and photographs from Lewis Chase, undated (Box 4)
      - Syllabus and exams, 1903 and undated (Box 4)
  - Shelley, Percy Bysshe (Box 4)
    - Criticism and notes, undated (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1910-1939 (Box 4)
    - Student papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Shenstone, William (Box 4)
    - Criticism and clippings, 1926-1939 (Box 4)
  - Sheridan, Richard (Box 4)
    - Clippings and notes, 1927-1940 and undated (Box 4)
    - Student paper, 1902 (Box 4)
  - Sidgwick, Frank (Box 4)
    - "Dedication to M." [photocopies], undated (Box 4)
    - "Form Fours" [photocopies], undated (Box 4)
    - "His Hirsute Suit" [photocopies], undated (Box 4)
    - "MacBeth and the Three Caskets" [photocopies], undated (Box 4)
    - "Publisher's Dedication" [photocopies], undated (Box 4)
  - Skelton, John (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1929-1939 and undated (Box 4)
  - Southey, Robert (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1922-1925 (Box 4)
  - Sterne, Laurence (Box 4)
    - Bibliography and student papers, undated (Box 4)
    - Notes, lectures, and clippings, 1905 and undated (Box 4)
  - Swift, Jonathan (Box 4)
    - Notes, lectures, and clippings, 1905-1941 and undated (Box 4)
  - Tennyson, Lord Alfred (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1906-1936 and undated (Box 4)
    - Criticism, 1917 (Box 4)
    - Lectures and notes, 1899 and undated (Box 4)
    - Student paper, 1907 (Box 4)
  - Thackeray, William (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1934-1940 (Box 4)
    - Lewis Chase's lectures [and notes], 1899 and undated (Box 4)
    - Student paper, 1928 (Box 4)
    - Thackeray Centenary, 1911 and undated (Box 4)
  - Trollope, Anthony (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1927-1940 and undated (Box 4)
  - Twain, Mark (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1905-1932 and undated (Box 4)
    - The Innocents Abroad, undated (Box 5)
    - Mark Twain's Funniest, undated, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - Roughing It, undated (Box 5)
    - Sketches New and Old, undated (Box 5)
    - Stories and excerpts, undated (Box 5)
    - 70th Birthday Souvenir Supplements, 1905 (Box 5)
  - Updike, John (Box 5)
    - National Book Award Speech, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Vaughan, Henry (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1924-1940 (Box 5)
  - Villon, Françoise (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1926-1928 (Box 5)
  - Vondel, Joost van der (1588-1678) (Box 5)
    - Criticism, undated (Box 5)
  - Wagner, Richard (Box 5)
    - Tristan and Isolde - reprint, undated (Box 5)
  - Watson, Thomas (Box 5)
    - Lewis Chase's notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Whitman, Walt (Box 5)
    - Notes, essays, and articles, 1955 and undated (Box 5)
  - Wordsworth, Dorothy (Box 5)
    - Clipping, 1927 (Box 5)
  - Wordsworth, William (Box 5)
    - English poetry, eighteenth century, 1921-1941 and undated (Box 5)
      - Clippings, 1921-1941 and undated (Box 5)
      - Notes, essays, and correspondence, 1936 and undated (Box 6)
    - General, 1908-1926 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Lewis Chase's clippings, 1902-1934 and undated (Box 6)
    - Chase's notes and lectures, 1900 and undated (Box 6)
    - "Resolution and Independence," undated (Box 6)
    - Student papers, 1907 and undated (Box 6)
    - Wordsworth in India, 1935 and undated (Box 6)
  - Wycherly, William (Box 6)
    - Notes and clippings, 1922-1940 and undated (Box 6)
- Subject Files Series, 1857-1969 and undated, bulk 1915-1969 (Box 6)
  Organized into groupings reflecting Gohdes's interests and projects: bibliographies, poetry, travel narratives of the American West, and UNESCO's best books list.
  The bibliographic materials contain issues of the Bulletin of Bibliography and bibliographic information that Gohdes requested, such as library holdings in literature in various areas, including Cleveland, St. Louis, and Balboa Heights (Canal Zone).
  The poetry files contain copies and mimeographs of late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century poetry. "Contemporary Poetry," "Modern Poetry" and "Poetry" all contain early twentieth century materials. The first folder, "Criticism and Reviews," contains reprints of essays and articles by various authors. The only original writing can be found in the second folder, "Introductory Lecture, University of Wisconsin," which Lewis Chase may have written.
  The "Travel Narratives and the West" folders contain photocopies and reproductions of nineteenth-century accounts of travel through the western United States, with some notes by Gohdes.